# Shuyue Jia (Bruce)

🖂 brucejia@bu.edu 🕿 +1 (617)-685-1479 🞧 GitHub 🤗 Hugging Face 🖫 Google Scholar 🗓 Personal Homepage

# CONTACT INFORMATION

**Telephone**: +1 (617)-685-1479 (USA), +852 5460-4494 (Hong Kong SAR)

Office Address: 15/F, Center for Computing & Data Sciences, 665 Commonwealth Ave., Boston, MA 02215, USA

Mail Address: Room 314, 3/F, 14 Buswell St., Boston, MA 02215, USA

Residence: Beijing, China & Xinzhou, Shanxi, China

Previous Residence: Jilin, Jilin, China & Kowloon, Hong Kong, China & Irvine, CA, USA Special Notice: Hong Kong SAR Resident & Hong Kong IANG Working VISA Holder

## RESEARCH INTERESTS AND STATEMENT

I am a Ph.D. student working on

- AI Foundation Models, e.g., Pre-trained Large Language Models (LLMs)
- Generative AI, e.g., Diffusion Probabilistic Models
- Reasoning with Foundation Models, e.g., equip LLMs with strong mathematical reasoning capability
- Visual and Language Multimodal Learning, e.g., CLIP
- AI for Medicine and Healthcare, e.g., Medical Imaging with AI
- Trustworthy AI

My ultimate goal is to **develop safe, reliable, and extensible Artificial General Intelligence systems** that can improve human lives. Source codes of all my works will be shared on  $\bigcirc$  GitHub, the trained models and datasets will be released on  $\bigcirc$  Hugging Face, and some of my applied research on Vision and Language will be developed as Web or Android/iOS mobile apps.

#### ACADEMIC APPOINTMENTS

## City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR Research Assistant

Sept 2021 - Apr 2023

- Supervisor: Prof. Shiqi Wang
- Project: Image Quality Assessment (IQA) and Perceptual Optimization

#### EDUCATION

## Boston University, Boston, Massachusetts, USA

Sept 2023 - Present

- Ph.D. in Computer Engineering, Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering
- Supervisor: Prof. Vijava B. Kolachalama @ Kolachalama Laboratory @ BU
- Expertise: Foundation Models, Generative Models, Vision and Language Multimodal Learning, Medical Imaging
- Financial Aids: Distinguished Computer Engineering Fellowship (USD \$39,780 per year)

## City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR, China

May 2021 - June 2023

- M.Phil. in Computer Science, Department of Computer Science
- Supervisor: Prof. Shiqi Wang
- Expertise: Image Quality Assessment and Perceptual Optimization
- Thesis: No-reference Image Quality Assessment via Non-local Modeling
- Financial Aids: Research Assistantship (HKD \$13,000 per month)

## Northeast Electric Power University, Jilin, Jilin, China

Sept 2016 - Jun 2020

- B.Eng. in Intelligence Science and Technology, School of Automation Engineering
- Supervisor: Prof. Yimin Hou, Prof. Jinglei Lv, and Prof. Yang Li
- Expertise: Neural Networks (Deep Learning)
- Thesis: Brain-computer Interface Signals Classification and Its Applications based on Deep Learning Methods
- Creator and Maintainer of GitHub repo EEG-DL (obtained 780+ stars and 200+ forks), a Deep Learning library written by TensorFlow for EEG Tasks (Signals) Classification

#### University of California, Irvine, Irvine, California, USA

Jul - Sept 2017

- Visiting Student, Summer School, Department of Computer Science
- Selected coursework: Computer Systems and Architecture (A+), University Writing and Communication (PASS)

### PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

#### **Journal Publications**

• GCNs-Net: A Graph Convolutional Neural Network Approach for Decoding Time-resolved EEG Motor Imagery Signals [ Paper] [ Codes] [ Slides] [ Survey]

Shuyue Jia, Yimin Hou, Xiangmin Lun, Ziqian Hao, Yan Shi, Yang Li, Rui Zeng, Jinglei Lv $^*$  IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems (IEEE T-NNLS)

- GitHub Repo obtained 780+ stars and 200+ forks
- Deep Feature Mining via Attention-based BiLSTM-GCN for Human Motor Imagery Recognition Shuyue Jia \*, Yimin Hou, Xiangmin Lun, Shu Zhang, Tao Chen, Fang Wang, Jinglei Lv [3 Paper] [ Codes] Frontiers in Bioengineering and Biotechnology
- A Novel Approach of Decoding EEG Four-Class Motor Imagery Tasks via Scout ESI and CNN [3 Paper] [ Codes] Yimin Hou, Lu Zhou \*, Shuyue Jia, Xiangmin Lun Journal of Neural Engineering
  - GitHub Repo obtained 150+ stars and 40+ forks
- PMU Measurements based Short-term Voltage Stability Assessment of Power Systems via Deep Transfer Learning [� Paper]

Yang Li \*, Shitu Zhang, Yuanzheng Li, Jiting Cao, **Shuyue Jia** *IEEE Transactions on Instrumentation and Measurement (IEEE T-IM)* 

- Learning from Mixed Datasets: A Monotonic Image Quality Assessment Model [8 Paper] [ Codes] Zhaopeng Feng, Keyang Zhang, Shuyue Jia, Baoliang Chen, Shiqi Wang \*

  \*\*IET Electronics Letters\*\*
- Improving Performance: A Collaborative Strategy for the Multi-data Fusion of Electronic Nose and Hyperspectral to Track the Quality Difference of Rice [E Paper]

Yan Shi, Hangcheng Yuan, Chenao Xiong, **Shuyue Jia**, Jingjing Liu, Hong Men \* Sensors & Actuators: B. Chemical

• Origin Traceability of Rice based on an Electronic Nose Coupled with a Feature Reduction Strategy [3 Paper] Yan Shi, Xiaofei Jia, Hangcheng Yuan, **Shuyue Jia**, Jingjing Liu, Hong Men \*

Measurement Science and Technology

# Conference and Workshop Publications

• No-reference Image Quality Assessment via Non-local Dependency Modeling [ Paper] [ Codes] [ Slides] [ Poster] Shuyue Jia, Baoliang Chen, Dingquan Li, Shiqi Wang \*

IEEE 24<sup>th</sup> International Workshop on Multimedia Signal Processing (IEEE MMSP'22) (Poster Presentation)

#### Thesis

No-reference Image Quality Assessment via Non-local Modeling [ Permanent Link] Defense Slides]
 Shuyue Jia
 M.Phil. Thesis, City University of Hong Kong, May 2023.

#### Note:

- 1. 7 Google Scholar Profile
- 2. \* denotes the Corresponding Author.

#### OPEN-SOURCE PROJECTS AND DATASETS

## Library - EEG Deep Learning Library (780+ stars and 200+ forks) [ Code]

• EEG-DL is a Deep Learning (DL) library written by TensorFlow for EEG tasks (signals) classification.

# Toolkit - PromptCraft [ Code | [PyPI Package |

• PromptCraft is a prompt perturbation toolkit from the character, word, and sentence levels for prompt robustness analysis.

## Benchmark Dataset - GSM8K-Consistency [Dataset (available on Page Hugging Face)]

• GSM8K-Consistency is a benchmark database for analyzing the consistency of Arithmetic Reasoning on GSM8K.

#### Paper Survey - Awesome LLM Self-Consistency [ Repo]

• Awesome LLM Self-Consistency is a curated list of self-consistency in Large Language Models (LLMs).

## 

• Awesome Semantic Textual Similarity is a curated list of Semantic/Sentence Textual Similarity (STS) in Large Language Models and the NLP Field.

#### Industry Experience

#### Samsung Research, Beijing

# Computer Vision Research Intern

May - Jun 2022

- Research Proposal: Temporally Consistent Instance Tracking for Video Panoptic Segmentation (VPS).
- Temporally consistent Instance Association: object high-level correspondence (instance embedding association) in consistency with the pixel low-level correspondence (optical flow).
- Generate Dense Mask: wrote scripts to generate dense masks by linear interpolation from the sparse masks. (Mentor: Dr. Hui Zhang)

## Philips Research, Shanghai

#### **NLP Research Intern**

Jul - Oct 2020

2016 - 2020

- Medical Concept Mapping: three levels to map the query to a standard term → BPE and FMM & BMM algorithms for sub-words generation and matching (syntax-level), word vector cosine similarity (semantics-level), and knowledge graph (pragmatics-level).
- Medical Terms NER: compared the performances of different models → CRF++, Character-level BiLSTM + CRF, Character-level BiLSTM + Word-level BiLSTM / CNNs + CRF, and deployed the models using Flask and Docker as web apps.
- Dynamic Webs Crawling: crawled 620,000 words from the NSTL via python parallel package threading and other tricks to prevent anti-reptile.

(Mentor: Dr. Shuang Zhou)

Fellowships and Scholarships

# AWARDS AND SERVICES

Distinguished Computer Engineering Fellowship, Boston University, USA	2023 - 2024
Research Assistantship, City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR	2021 - 2023
Innovation Scholarship, Northeast Electric Power University, China	2017 - 2019

Excellent Student Scholarship, Northeast Electric Power University, China

# Mathematics and Physics Competition Awards

2019 Interdisciplinary Contest In Modeling, USA Honorable Mention	[ Thesis (English)] Apr 2019
2018 Mathematical Contest In Modeling, Jilin, China	[ Thesis (Chinese)] Aug 2018
2018 Interdisciplinary Contest In Modeling, USA	[harmonic Thesis (English)] Apr 2018
2017 National English Competition for College Students, China	May 2017
2015 National English Proficiency Competition for Secondary School Students, China	First Prize Dec 2015
The $32^{nd}$ Chinese Physics Olympiad (CPhO), China $\ensuremath{\textit{Third Prize}}$	Oct 2015
2015 National High School Math League, China Second Prize	Sept 2015

#### **Sports Competition Awards**

2022 Standard Chartered Hong Kong Marathon, Full Marathon	Feb 2023
2021 Hangzhou International Marathon, Half Marathon	Apr 2022
City U Top 5 Runner, City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR $\textbf{\textit{The}}\ 1^{st}\ \textbf{\textit{Place}}$	Oct 2021
2021 Standard Chartered Hong Kong Marathon, Half Marathon $\it Rank~318~/~6000~(01:38:14)$	Oct 2021
2018 National Marathon Championships (Jilin City Station), Full Marathon	Jun 2018
2017 National Marathon Championships (Jilin City Station), Half Marathon $\ Rank\ 148\ /\ 5000\ (01:47:36)$	$\mathrm{Jun}\ 2017$
Outstanding Athlete, Northeast Electric Power University, China	May 2017
3000-meter Steeplechase, The $45^{th}$ NEEPU Games, Northeast Electric Power University, China $\it The~7^{th}~\it Place$	May 2017

## Leadership Awards

Vice Chairman, International Communication Association, Northeast Electric Power University, China	Jun 2019
Outstanding Student Leader Awards, Northeast Electric Power University, China	Oct 2018

#### Reviewer

Check from Web of Science	
IEEE Transactions on Multimedia (T-MM)	2023
IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Video Technology (T-CSVT)	2023

IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics (JBHI)	2020, 2023
IEEE Sensors Journal	2023
Analytical Methods	2023
Postharvest Biology and Technology	2022
Scientific Reports	2023, 2024
Energy Reports	2023
Membership	
China Computer Federation (CCF)	Since 2017
Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)	Since 2019
IEEE Student Chapter/IEEE Eta Kappa Nu (IEEE-HKN), Boston University	Since 2023
Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)	Since 2019
Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)	Since 2022
ACM Special Interest Group on Artificial Intelligence (SIGAI)	Since 2022
ACM Special Interest Group on Multimedia (SIGMM)	Since 2022
ACM Special Interest Group on Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH)	Since 2023
ACM Special Interest Group on Security, Audit and Control (SIGSAC)	Since 2023
Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)	Since 2023
American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS)	Since 2023
Linguistic Society of America (LSA)	Since 2023
Volunteer	
IEEE Boston Section, Boston, MA, USA	2024

#### INVITED TALKS

1. AI In the 2020s And Beyond

Presentation Sept 2023

Invited Talk at The Construction of the Management Disciplines (CoME), Tianjin University, Tianjin, China.

# Professional Skills

Coding: Python, C/C++, MATLAB, R, Mathematica, HTML

Library: TensorFlow, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Hugging Face (Transformers, PEFT, Datasets, etc.), vLLM

 $\textbf{Tools}\text{: }\operatorname{Git, \, SVN, \, Unix \, Shell, \, Vim, \, Markdown, \, L\!\!\!\!^{A}T_{\!E}\!X, \, Docker, \, K8s}$ 

Hardware: NVIDIA Jetson Nano (Ubuntu), Raspberry Pi (Raspbian OS), 80C52 Microcontroller (Embedded C) Hobby: Photography, Hiking, Mountain Climbing, Soccer, Skateboarding, Cycling, Coding, Marathon, Cooking

#### References

Prof. Shiqi Wang, Associate Professor

Address: Room Y6414, 6/F, Department of Computer Science, Yeung Kin Man Academic Building, City University of

Hong Kong, #83 Tat Chee Avenue, Kowloon Tong, Hong Kong SAR

Homepage: https://www.cs.cityu.edu.hk/shiqwang/

Email: shiqwang@cityu.edu.hk

**Tel**: +852-3442-7341

Prof. Jinglei Lv, Senior Lecturer

Address: M02F, Building F, Brain and Mind Centre & School of Biomedical Engineering, The University of Sydney, 94

Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW, Australia

Homepage: https://www.sydney.edu.au/engineering/about/our-people/academic-staff/jinglei-lv.html

Email: jinglei.lv@sydney.edu.au

**Tel**: +61-4114-37661

#### Prof. Yimin Hou, Full Professor and Vice Dean

Address: Vice Dean Office (Room 434), 4/F, No. 1 Building, School of Automation Engineering, Northeast Electric

Power University, 169 Changchun Road, Jilin, Jilin, China **Homepage**: https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/author/37290052900

Email: houyimin@neepu.edu.cn

**Tel**: +86-158-4325-4264

#### Prof. Yang Li, Full Professor

Address: Room 525, 5/F, Power and Energy Building, School of Electrical Engineering, Northeast Electric Power

University, 169 Changchun Road, Jilin, Jilin, China

Homepage: http://meyangli.com/

**Email**: liyang@neepu.edu.cn **Tel**: +86-159-4796-6691